I thank the colleagues and the institutions who joined the French in their grief.
Dear colleagues, France always defeated its agressors, and once again, we will defeat them,
but we won't get lost in surveillance fantasies, and I hope
we won't lose sight of the principles that have always driven its republican history.
In the times we are living, I think that virtue mainly consists in the faculty of discernment.
We would be better off avoiding to talk about a clash of civilisations in this assembly or elsewhere, because what we are going through is not a clash of civilisations,
for the reason that ISIS is not a civilization but a totalitarianism.
It is not a clash of civilizations because we are not dealing with fighters, but with cowardly murderers who attacked defenseless people by surprise.
I speak of discernment because Islam, as any other belief, is not involved in this situation.
Once again, a war for money and by money hides behind religious fundamentalism.
We should also renounce in blaming poverty as the cause of crime.
Crime doesn't have any social origin! Crime comes from ideology and humans from all social backgrounds.
It would be a good thing if we did not stigmatize so easily such and such neighborhood
when the children of the rich and poor can be killed by lunatics.
We should remember that
those who asked for the reducing of state sovereign functions have a responsibility.
In my country, police manpower has been reduced by 12,000 officers, and the army manpower has decreased by 20%.
It is one of the causes that contributed to the lack of means that prevented to ward off the attacks on our country.
We should stop implementing these policies that weaken public services, and we should stop
being blind, amnesic and indulgent towards countries
that but do as ISIS and other groups do, but on a large scale, using the institutions of their state.
Terrorism comes from the wars between powers that try to control a region
where immense wealth is produced and controled.
Therefore, terrorism will cease when war will cease!
It is not through the gathering of information about the population of Europe that we will know more than we already know about dangerous individuals.
Terrorism comes from war, we therefore need to stop war.
Terrorism comes from money, we therefore need to stop money laundering.
I am in favor of a universal coalition, because humanity as a whole is concerned about this issue.
A universal coalition under the auspices of the only institution that is universally competent, the UNO.
Let us share the motto of the Enlightenment in this dark hours, that was appropriated by my country
and offered to all humanity: "Liberty, Equality, Fraternity", and not "Passenger Name Record for everyone"!